[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
signalwire real-time video technology
allows you to create interactive video
experiences that were previously
impossible signalwire gives developers
access to broadcast quality ultra low
latency video for everything from video
collaboration tools for film and tv
studios and fortune 500 enterprises to
engaging virtual events they can even
assist with one-of-a-kind fully
interactive virtual concerts see why the
future of video communication is being
built on signal wire they're easy to
deploy apis and sdks are available in
most popular programming languages
signal wire is a complete unified
platform for integrating video as well
as voice and messaging capabilities into
any application try today at
signalwire.com and use code se radio for
25 in developer credit go to
signalwire.com that's signalwire.com and
use code se radio to receive twenty five
dollars in developer credit today
[Music]
for software engineering radio this is
robert blumen i have with me today
leonie chefsof
leonid or as he goes by leo is a
software architect at railsware a
company that offers email testing
products he has over 13 years of
experience building software for the web
the past year and a half he has been
developing a mail transfer agent we will
be talking about email generally
transactional email and bulk email leo
welcome to software engineering radio
hey robert it's nice to be here would
you like to add anything to your
background that i didn't cover uh
well.mta has been in two years in
development now
it's taking a while
yeah smtp is a
fascinating technology i'm excited to
talk about it we started out thinking
about transactional and bulk email as a
topic
i wanted to spend some time talking
about email generally because we all use
it but it's probably
not as widely understood as some newer
technologies like http
so let's start out talking about email
and then we'll talk about some more
modern applications are you familiar
with the history of email not really i'm
not a much of a historian but i can tell
you that smtp is pretty much as
old or older than the web and it's uh
pretty amazing that it survived this far
it's a very open i would say it's the
most open messaging format on the
internet and in these days when we take
much care into decentralization and
like moving away from
just
allowing people to
participate in a platform
well
smtp has allowed
individual people even to participate
without any like center
from the beginning it originated in
universities
so
every university had a server with
people on it and
sometimes they exchange mail on the
server and that was relatively easy to
do but then uh what if you want to send
mail to someone outside of your own
university or
domain as we now
call such things so
that's when smgp was born and
it is basically a protocol to send mail
from one domain to another that's what
it is smtp being an acronym what does
that stand for oh it's just a simple
mail transfer protocol or simple message
transfer protocol doesn't say much so
smtp as i said is extremely
decentralized
and all you need to
send mail is a domain name or perhaps
you can even get away with an ap address
but you really want a domain name and
once you have that you can send mail you
can do that from your own machine you
can do that from your application server
or maybe you should not do that
because of reasons that we'll talk later
it's fascinating that while smtp was
designed as a protocol for humans now
it's
the the vast majority of emails you send
from
automated systems it's bulk mail and the
worst of bulk mail is of course spam
messaging and uh protecting people from
unwanted mail is the is a huge and it's
it's the most important uh thing going
on in email for
years and years and there's no
side no no no end in sight in that
matter i want to situate
smtp let's
go
one level higher
from
where we are what is the overall
structure of
email delivery uh so smtp is a text
protocol just like http and to deliver
mail you just connect to
a port so that's that would be a port
well for clients is usually 587 and for
servers it's 25 and then you
have a text dialogue with the server so
compose and send the mail from your
machine
your mail app will communicate with a
mail transfer agent which is a server
that runs smtp protocol and it will
cue your message for delivery and uh in
the next possible moment which hopefully
is like within a second it will uh
determine uh through the dns system what
is the other the the recipients uh mail
transfer agent uh connect to it and
deliver the mail and the recipient
transfer agent will
put the mail in a some form of a mailbox
and usually let the recipient know that
there's a new message and then the
recipient can go and use
one of the standard
mailbox protocols of which there are two
uh pop3 and imap and uh read the message
does the
mail go directly from the sending smtp
server to the recipient or
can it transit over intermediaries or
proxies yeah that's an interesting
question so
the way the protocol is structured it
seems like there's multiple servers in
the chain and
you would think that there's like to
deliver mail it has to go through hops
like you would see in an ip community ap
packet communicating actually uh there's
usually just two servers the sender
server and the recipient server and what
might happen is that either of those
have several servers in their internal
chain for example there's
such a
service on the web as
a pre-filter that will reject spam
messages so you can that that is another
kind of smtp server smtp relay that you
use in place of your own smtp and that
it will filter the messages and it will
forward the legit messages to your uh
mta so then you would have a two servers
on the receiver end of the
sntp message flow and on the sender end
for example maybe you have some internet
server for your enterprise company or
university which will then go through a
relay before leaving the intranet to go
to someone else's mta let's start out
with an email address what are the
components of the email address yeah so
as i said
all
mail is attached to a domain so the
domain is what you see before the add
sign in an email address and it defines
where does your mailbox live so it
defines where to send mail so it gets to
you and the
uh part to the left of the ad sign is
your it's not your username it's
actually not that well defined because
it the behavior of that part depends on
the specific
mail server that you're running well
it's usually the name of a mailbox on
the server but it doesn't have to be
it's just some identifier looking more
in depth at the domain name the sending
side will use dns to locate a recipient
what kind of dns query does it make what
does it get back
yeah so there's a standard dns record
which is the mx record which
points to the mail server for a specific
domain so a mail domain that record
specifies where is the mail server for
your domain
and where would in mta connect to send
mail
so it is received by your domain because
in many many cases the
domain
that is for example serving the website
is not the same domain which would
receive mail that would be on convenient
so you can define a separate domain name
for the mail server or multiple i want
to clarify do you mean i might have a
domain or you might have a domain say
it's
mail.mailtrap.com
and we're going to send mail there or
you might use mailtrap.com but the mx
record would have a different ip address
than the website
the differences in the domain name and
the ip addresses
they
don't matter as much let's have a more
familiar example so if you're using
google apps for your domain so you have
software engineering.com and then but
you're actually using google apps so you
don't host your own mail server it's
served by google so the mx record for
the domain would then be something like
aspmx.somethingsomething.google.com
and when i want to send mail to software
engineering.com and i compose a message
then my mta will look up the mx record
and will see that it has to send the
mail to google which is another
fascinating thing about smtp and mail
that while it is designed and imagined
as a decentralized protocol it's the
vast majority of mail is hosted on the
same big corporate servers like google
is there an authentication component for
the user to send an email
yes of course
as any other service
you have to authenticate so the
authentication happens
on the
first leg of the flow when your user
application connects to the first
submission agent the first mta in the
chain it will authenticate and it
usually requires a username and password
and then the rest of the way the mail is
actually not authenticated in that way
so the rest of the communication is
literally open for anyone else that is a
big challenge in delivering mail what
are some of the problems caused by that
in two words that means that anyone can
deliver a mail that looks like you sent
it there's no mechanism stopping that
there are mechanism mechanisms that
would allow the receiver to verify that
the message is sent from you but anyone
can try to just connect to recipients
mta and deliver message from anyone in
the world in practice is that something
that happens a lot it does happen a lot
with spam mail there are pretty good
mechanisms to stop well to detect the
mail before it gets to a user because
people are easy to confuse and computers
are sometimes less so however
the idea of spam is that if you send a
billion messages then maybe a thousand
comes through and you have some result
so they just
find strength and numbers and abuse the
email system with
much more mail than normal if i
understand then any computer anywhere
with an smtp server could look up
another smtp server and send the mail
and say this mail is from robert blumen
at sc radio
dot net there isn't anything in the
protocol
inherently that would verify
or reject that as being not true that is
correct that anyone can connect and send
such an email so what are some of the
mechanisms that have been built to
validate senders yeah so there are two
major mechanisms first one is spf it's
the older one and spf is another type of
a dns record that specifies the allowed
senders for your domain so for example
you can state that only your mta can
send mail or some specific ap can send
mail for your domain or
well that those are the two options
really
that way when the recipient receives an
email they can check the origin and if
it doesn't match the spf record then
they
know that it's not from you the problem
with that is that relies on
so setups
fluctuate so
spf records often become invalid so
rejecting a mail just on the basis of
spf would result in many false positives
and that's why it's not a
hard rule to accept or reject email and
the other mechanism is dkim which
is
essentially a signature for the mail and
the way it works is
again with the dns record
so you publish the public key for the
signature in your dns record and then
you use the private key to sign the mail
and then the recipient again can verify
that the signature meshes the public key
in the demand record and the way this is
problematic is also because uh
setups fluctuate
and uh
that's one problem and the other problem
is
signing messages is not very simple so
it's simple if you're
running an mta but it's not simple if
you're just sending mail
from
like your own machine which is a thing
you can do so requiring
such a mechanism to be present always
would cut off many people from the
male ecosystem and for a practical
example of where you send mail
without
any
big mta
is if you're just
running a script on your server and you
want to get the results and you don't
want to complicate the setup you can
just use send mail which is a unix
utility present on most machines and you
just
use it to connect directly to the
recipient mta and deliver your mail and
this mostly works the spf and dkim
records are those a type of dns record
yes yes those are dns records you would
host them with your dns provider exactly
and the owner of the domain sets them up
so that's the
the trust part there so you have to own
the domain and have access to the dns
setup to modify them so what you
described is if you were to strictly
use those frameworks you might end up
rejecting too many emails given that how
widely used are those
two
practices they are used by any sander
that wants to appear trusted so i would
say they are
used in all of the
mail going on unless it's a
like hobby server for example there is
little reason not to use them and that
is that also poses a problem if i'm a
large retailer i have two million
customers
people sign up for email because they
want to know what are the deals this
week so we're talking about a totally
legitimate type of email which people
have opted in and i want to be sure that
this email doesn't run into any problems
at all with any kind of filtering that
might take place or spam detection then
i would set up an spf and dkim because
if i am legitimate why not is
that more or less correct yes that
that's one case where you definitely
want an spf and dkm but the problem is
that the spammers will also set up spf
and dkam and that's another reason why
the mechanisms are not very robust
so if i set up a domain that looks like
your domain with a slight difference
i can completely
correctly set up spf and dk dkm for that
domain and send mail that appears well
it is sent from that domain and it is
validly sent and it's a completely
legitimately signed email but it's still
coming from a domain that is designed to
mislead the user into thinking that it's
for example their bank which is called
spoofing what you're talking about is
the spammer can prove that the email did
originate from the domain that it said
it's simply not a good domain which is a
different problem
exactly and domains are
also widely accessible so
there's no mechanism stopping spammers
from registering registering more and
more domains let's drill down a little
bit into smtp so you have the
two sides of the protocol
what are the messages that are exchanged
in an smtp session a mail message
looks very similar to an http
response it uses the same header and
body structure so if
you've seen an http request it's just
the same uh there are several required
headers like from or two and uh
many optional headers of which there's
the dkim signature header and some
headers that serve other communicative
purposes or they're used for tracking
mailing lists and then there's a body
which is
either in html or text document or an
attachment which is base64 encoded so
it's all in all the same format as http
requests
just with different flavors the whole
process from beginning to end i would
imagine a large number of things could
go wrong and we don't have time to talk
about all of them but what are some of
the major
things that can fail in
causing email not to get through all
right so
first of all i'd like to mention that
smtp is an asynchronous protocol so it's
designed to operate when your recipient
is not home
and that's why it was created because
if you want to send a message
you want someone to receive it while the
person maybe not at their computer and
will receive so that's why you have mail
servers
and uh well first of all
you have to have a mail server running
on the recipient and uh well and on the
center end to
get the message through but that is an
obvious one
you have to have the
domain records the mx domain record set
up correctly so that
your mta can find where to deliver the
mail
you have to
then be able to connect to their
domain
and
then you have to
provide a valid
mailbox name on that domain and then
there are internal rules
such as
mailbox size
because of which the receiving mta might
reject your message so if the mailbox is
full
it will reject the message
if there's no mailbox it will reject the
message
and if your email does not pass
reputation checks it will also reject
the message
and all of those are called the bounces
in mail lingo so a bounce is where you
connect to the server the recipient
server
and
it does not accept your message we have
at this point a pretty good broad
overview of email and now i want to move
into a particular more modern
application which is called
transactional email and that's something
you have expertise in i want to start
out defining it term transaction it's
heavily overloaded in computing what
does it mean in the context of email yes
in email
transactions
are not the same that a programmer would
be used to because email uses the term
in more of a business context and and
transaction just means some thing
happening that leads to an email being
sent so it's like an event in programmer
terms but i also don't want to
attach too much meaning to the event
word so
transactional mail simply means mail
directed to a specific
recipient
for a specific individual reason and
that is in contrast to
bulk mail where you have a message that
you want to send to many people
sometimes it's millions of people and
some very different
mechanisms apply when you need to send
just one message versus a million
it's not going to be helpful if i think
database transaction this is more like i
bought something and the transaction is
more of a transaction in the business
sense is that correct yes yes well what
are some examples of transactional
emails some use cases well the most
transactional emails are those that
have to
occur
at the instance that they were requested
for example if you're receiving login
credentials or if you reset a password
and then
in the order of decreasing priority so
maybe you want an order update and that
could also happen instantly so sending
mail instantly is harder than sending it
on a schedule or with a delay and for
example a password you want to receive
uh instantly and we really are irritated
when it doesn't arrive
fast and for an order update it doesn't
happen because of your actions so while
it is still directed to you personally
it's not a problem if it's delayed a bit
so maybe you want to
bulk send order updates to collect them
like in a uh some buffer and then there
are some
quasi marketing emails like the welcome
the onboarding message it might be a
transactional message or
usually a bulk message and then you go
into complete the marketing territory
where you just send me messages on a
schedule
everything goes as expected what is a
pretty good
time frame between sending and receiving
an email
sending itself is uh very fast so it
would take within a second if
everything goes well and the time over
that delivery time is queuing
in case the mta your mta is
over capacity or
you might also see slower delivery
because of
intermittent bounces what are the main
difficulties in
implementing transactional email so
transactional mail is usually sent
by
some application right so
someone runs a web application and
the first idea you might have is that as
i said you can just send the mail from
the server you're
running the application on
and the
tricky part is that that's completely
valid and possible and
if you're just
running linux you have send mail you can
just send send the mail to the recipient
and then you start running into problems
the
biggest problem of
all i would say is that
unless you process
the bounces
and the spam reports that occur
so if you're not being a good male
citizen
and
you're just sending mail with no
understanding
where it ends up you
quickly get
blacklisted so
the a part of your reputation is uh
how many pounds messages how many
messages that qualify as spam you send
and that doesn't matter that there are
spam messages because mechanisms are not
perfect these spam algorithms are
perfect so anyone can send a message
that looks like spam and the proper
thing to do in this case is to detect
that and adjust your message or do not
send it if the recipient rejects it and
that is hard to do when you are running
and delivering mail from your own server
on your
own efforts so that's the big challenge
there's also the one that you have to
set up all the spf and dkm and run
signatures
so that kind of thing but that is a
one-off problem and processing rejects
is an ongoing problem that you have to
do constantly stroll down into the
bounce you said bounce is a general term
for many different kinds of failures
does the point in the system where the
bounce occurs generate a return message
back to the sender so a bounce is
specifically a failure that happens at
the moment of delivery so you always get
a message back at that instance and it
usually describes what's going on
and by that message you classify bounces
as soft bounces and hard bounces
and this is not a
well-defined distinction it's just that
south bounces are something that might
resolve in some time for example if the
mail server is over capacity
or if the mailbox is full that might get
resolved and if there's no such
recipient
then
there's no chance you're gonna
deliver the mail later so the proper way
to do in such case is not send the mail
again and that's called the hard bounds
sc radio listeners we want to hear from
you
please visit se radio.net survey to
share a little information about your
professional interests and listening
habits it takes less than two minutes to
help us continue to make se radio even
better
the responses to the survey are
completely confidential that's
s-e-radio.net
thanks for your support of the show we
look forward to hearing from you soon
[Music]
you mentioned that if i
write a script on a server it can
correctly execute the protocols but it
doesn't the ability to handle some of
these error cases does that suggest an
architecture where the application would
submit email requests to a subsystem
that's better able to deal with the
failure modes
uh yes that's the reason uh
mail transfer agents
as service exist is because you want
some third-party handling uh errors for
you
uh you want them to do monitoring
and uh
you want to know that
the
errors don't
end up in the void
so what i didn't mention is that beyond
besides bounces there is also
a case where
someone marks the message as spam
which is a different kind of error and
that does generate a
separate message
to your mail server which is like
another smtp message
and you have to parse and
process that
and
also record probably record the
recipient as a
non-deliverable and
processing
mail messages is not an easy task to do
i've tried it in the past i've tried to
send mail from my server and process
bounces and process
return messages
and
it's not something that
can be done reasonably if it's not your
main focus
what are the difficulties in getting it
right
well uh there's just that it's a
separate
service to run
and then the
formative messages
is
variable based on the
recipient mta
there's no hard standard for these
messages
they're all as i mentioned text-based
and the
there are error codes but they also vary
and there's
the error codes have deep nesting so you
might parse a generic error code like
mailbox full but not parse the specifics
and uh
you
don't you can't just pull up a protocol
spec and implement implemented
that's not possible in this case you
have to
with time or time collect more message
formats
and
build your
sort of database algorithm of handling
the messages
and that's what mta's do if a mailbox is
full i would expect to get a bounce
pretty quickly but something might sit
in somebody's inbox for a few days and
they mark it as spam the indication that
email was considered spam could come
back much later is that correct
yes it can come at any time
you're sending emails and then
immediately or much later you get
different kinds of error codes coming
back how do you associate the error
messages coming back with the messages
that went out there's a
standard for that at least
when
you send a mail you specify
something called
a variable envelope return path which is
a complicated way of saying it's and the
address that you want the
uh the non-delivery uh
report to
be delivered to
and that
that address is an example of
an address that does not correspond to a
mailbox on the server because the
the username the local name in that
address is an encoded string that
contains
usually either the message id
or the recipient address or some other
whatever
your mte needs to identify a message
that failed are bounces sent back by
smtp well no bounces are just a in
protocol it's like an http response code
so you send a mail and you get back a
status code and some text back even if
the bounce comes back a day
later no no the bounces always come at
the moment of delivery okay so that's
right okay
something marked as spam
is that sent is that an smtp
message to
so to collect those you have to not only
run you need not only have to
send mail but you also need to have a
receiving mte because that's a message
that's going to be sent to you
and then you have to receive the message
and then you have to parse it
find the recipient mail
find the reason for the report and
record it in some database which you
will check
against
when sending future mail
what does that look like you have a
database you've collected bounces some
of which might clear in a short time
some which are considered permanent
failures and you have these async
delayed spam reports what do you do with
that information well it's not anything
complicated really
soft monsters usually go to the same
queue without a permanent
record anywhere so you just retry the
message
in a couple of minutes then in an hour
then maybe in a day
and then within two days of the initial
delivery you just fail or if you just
get a hard bounce or if you get a spam
report then
those records go into a table which
lists the
the recipients mail addresses and uh a
status code that says why would you not
send mail to them and some of these
expire over time like mailbox full could
be expired in a week or otherwise you
just don't
when you send you mail the recipient
address is checked against the table and
the mail is rejected
before sending and uh that is also how
unsubscribes work so you you also by the
way have to have a mechanism for
unsubscribes
uh that is
a crucial part of delivering mail
in our times because it is used by
uh recipient mtas
to
mark your messages not spam so if you
don't have an unsubscribe link
that is one of the factors that mark
your message as spam what happens when
someone unsubscribes
they get added to the
the table of unsubscribes
it's again that part at least is
very simple
so
you click on subscribe
you usually see some
long encoded
key in the url
that key contains
encoded information about
well who you are and
it puts the information into the
unsubscribes table and the good
unsubscribe mechanism doesn't require
you to log in anywhere it just just
works on the mail delivery layer and it
doesn't need any more information that
this contained with the unsubscribe link
i'm talking about
range of different components of
infrastructure
mil transfer agents processing of uh
unsubscribe processing of things marked
as spam how much of this does there
exist open source and how much of it is
commercial so
while there are many open source mtas to
name some
well-known ones so postfix is the one
that probably most people are familiar
with and it's shipped with linux
there's also ex im
if you want something fresh and
interesting to play with there's haraka
and zone mta
those are two ones that i experimented
with
but unfortunately when it comes to
actually
processing the error messages
and
doing delivery at scale
there's no
open source solutions for that because
building the knowledge base required is
uh
a it requires a lot of human resource
and that's how i understand it
so
first of all people usually want to get
paid for that and second of all it's too
much of a niche product to attract many
volunteers
so you don't see
good open source products in that
category what does the vendor space look
like how many vendors are there and is
it
typically
segmented by um a country or language or
are there
major worldwide players in that space so
if we're talking about the proprietary
mtas
as software
there are
several of them
and
some are
well i've seen i've seen u.s oriented
mtas and european oriented mtas and i'm
not sure if that's a big distinction in
terms of what they can process because
everybody sends mail worldwide these
days or rather just the regional
flavor i guess
but what i
can say is that
those that that software is usually
employed by
companies like hosting providers
or big enterprises that
need to send the
mail
for their clients
or if you're
building
your own empty so you might use
one of the solutions and then build your
business logic on top of that
if you
want to send mail for your application
you usually want
some
software as a service
and that is because
the licensing costs of proprietary mtas
do not suit
individual senders and on top of that
you also have to run your own
infrastructure which might get
complicated and expensive if you're
sending at scale next thing i want to
talk about is testing how do you go
about
testing transactional emails with so
many pieces and it's so highly
distributed
to
test mail you usually deliver it to
someone so you want to exercise the
protocol otherwise you you just stop the
delivery so
historically what people have done is
just send mail to their own account they
own their own mailbox and
see what comes up and uh
incidentally uh
working at mail trap so we build the
service
to
serve as the
submission mta
that will
collect your mail and then
collect it into a mailbox so you can see
uh what
your application is sending
instead of
using your own mailbox for that
because there are many issues with
sending mail out of into the world even
if it's into your own mailbox
the first of all being
that you might send to the wrong mailbox
to the wrong people
so if you have
some staging environment
and you have real
user emails which happens i've seen that
happen
and you send mail like you're testing a
mailing list
and you send mail to everybody on the
server and you spam real people
and that
is always a problem sometimes it makes
the news
and
to avoid that
we
build the mail trap which is an mta
that instead of delivering mail to the
recipient collects it and displays it
and gives you all sorts of analytics
so that's the kind of solution you want
to have when
testing that
your
mail would be delivered correctly so
what you want to see is uh
if your application is composing the
email correctly if you have the right
headers you want
if
your message looks right and if it
doesn't qualify as spam based on the
contents
so there's a
software called spam assassin
that analyzes
the
content of the message itself
if that looks like spam and it's
one of the factors used to analyze
to to sort
spam messages from non-spam so you want
to see
uh that your message scores well on spam
assassin you also want to see if
the application you're sending from is
not on a blacklisted server
if your domain is not blacklisted so
there's our those are things that you
want to know
before you start sending email to real
customers
you've mentioned blacklisting a couple
times and the first time you said it i
wanted to ask a question and then i and
i forgot describe who maintains a
blacklist and how do
servers either get on them or get off
them yeah so there are many companies
many third-party companies that operate
blacklists and
the idea of blacklist is well it's a
list of aps or domain names that
are not
trusted reliable email senders and that
doesn't mean they send spam necessarily
it's important to understand that well
there is legitimate spam there's also
mail that is either unsolicited and or
it appears like spam and you usually you
don't want to send those messages
because you get blacklisted
so there are two kinds of there's
actually there are two parts to
reputation management in mail so there
are two kinds of blacklists
one is attached to domains domain names
and those are the domain name that
you're sending from
so for example if you
as i mentioned if you're a spammer that
tries to fish passwords out of users by
appearing as
a
domain of some bank
then
your
phishing domain
might get blacklisted because it sends
spam
and
the other kind of blacklists is ip
blacklists
and they serve a different purpose
so spammers
usually
abuse
machines on the internet
and that's also a huge
interesting uh
area so
the main purpose actually to
hack into servers these days is to send
mail from them
you want some fresh ips
that's what hackers are against they
usually don't want to steal passwords
unless you're someone big
but they do want to
get your ip because every fresh ap is an
opportunity to send some mails before
getting blacklisted
once
male
recipients
see a large volume of spam
coming from some ip
so they cooperate with these blacklist
companies and they collect the
information about which ips are sending
unsolicited mail
and
sometimes the blacklists operate in a
matter of
minutes or hours so they're very highly
dynamic because
if someone hacks a machine
they just start abusing it right away
and it's important to stop the activity
as soon as it happens
and to get off such a blacklist
so there's again i think there's maybe
20 or 30 companies that run blacklists
and
you usually use a
tool to
see if your domain or ap is listed
and then you can appeal to the
individual company and
ask to
be removed from the blacklist
and the way you
actually get on the blacklist as a
legitimate sender is either you
inherit an ap that has a bad reputation
so that happens with cloud providers
although recently i think like amazon
cracked down on
spam sending so you can't send mail from
amazon machines
before they approve you
so that helps a bit so the ips are more
clean but in
the past decade there is a big problem
big big big problem that
if we with a cloud provider you get an
ip and it's already blacklisted
or
another
case is if you run mail and as i
mentioned you don't
check if it's qualified as spam and you
eventually get blacklisted unknownly and
then hopefully you start investigating
the issues here blacklisted
and you learn from the mistakes
we have in the last few minutes i wanted
to talk a bit more about bulk email
you've mentioned scale a couple of times
in the context of you could have a very
large number of transactional emails
like a very large number of order
updates or
businesses so large that you're doing a
large volume of password resets what are
particular challenges if i have a
mailing list with
2 million people and i want to get out 2
million emails in a reasonably short
span of time like maybe overnight to let
everybody know what are all the sales or
specials going on in my business the
next day that's an important target to
meet
so
many
emails are time sensitive
order updates are maybe not the most
time sensitive because
imagine you have to send
calendar event updates or like flight
cancellation updates
and
you really want people to receive them
right on time order updates of course
and
when you need to send
many messages at once
you usually use an mt that's tuned for
not transactional mail but bulk email
and
they have
a bigger array of
machines to send from but also
they can so a lot of time
that it takes to send the mail is
preparing the mail to be sent so
templating for example is
an obvious one so you have to prepare
the you have to render the mail
and the bulk message system would render
many emails more efficiently than one by
one so that's when you go to bulk sender
but i have to state that the box ending
in transactional sending are two
categories that while they intersect you
usually know if you want one or the
other
and
i would suggest
people to start with transactional
senders while they're small
because they are more controllable they
are so they are event driven you can
send just one mail and with the bulk
sender you usually have to submit like a
mailing list so start with a
transactional sender and when you get to
that million of customers you might
transition to bulk sander we've reached
the end of our time
is there anything else you wanted to
cover that we haven't talked about
before we wrap up
not really again to
repeat my uh suggestions to people who
start out sending mail i suggest
use
email as a service mt is as a service
because
you avoid many
rookie problems
test your mail before sending
uh
yeah don't send spam where can listeners
find you on the internet
they can find
me personally at the l
s dot me i have a blog on technology uh
they can find uh many interesting things
on mail on the mailchimp blog at
mailchimp.ioslash blog that's
it lanny thank you so much for speaking
to
software engineering radio
thank you this has been robert blumen
thank you for listening
sc radio listeners we want to hear from
you
please visit s e radio.net survey to
share a little information about your
professional interests and listening
habits it takes less than two minutes to
help us continue to make se radio even
better
the responses to the survey are
completely confidential that's
s-e-radio.net survey
thanks for your support of the show we
look forward to hearing from you soon
[Music]
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening